# Xiaowei Ren

PhD at the University of British Columbia Cell: (+1)778-893-7616

471, 6335 Thunderbird Residence, UBC Email: renxiaowei66@gmail.com / xiaowei@ece.ubc.ca

Vancouver, BC Canada, V6T 2G9 Homepage: https://ericrxw.github.io/xiaoweiren/

### Research Interest

I work in computer architecture and computer systems. My PhD research mainly focuses on (1) architectural support for efficient synchronization in single-GPU and multi-GPU systems, including memory consistency model, cache coherence protocol, transactional memory, and so on; (2) scalable graphics rendering in multi-GPU systems; (3) hardware acceleration for training sparse neural network directly.

### Education

Sept. 2015 – Present PhD in Computer Engineering University of British Columbia, Canada

Thesis: Efficient Synchronization Mechanisms for Scalable GPU Architectures

Sept. 2012 – Jun. 2015 MASc in Computer Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University, China

Thesis: Parallel Acceleration Algorithms and FPGA Implementation for KLMS and KAP

Sept. 2008 – Jun. 2012 BSc in Electronic Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University, China

## **Professional Experience**

Sept. 2015 – Present	Research Assistant	University of British Columbia, Canada
Sept. 2019 – Nov. 2019	Research Intern	Max Planck Institute for Software Systems, Germany
Aug. 2018 – Nov. 2018	Research Intern	NVIDIA Architecture Research Group, USA
May. 2017 – Aug. 2017	Research Intern	NVIDIA Architecture Research Group, USA
Sept. 2012 – Jun. 2015	Research Assistant	Xi'an Jiaotong University, China
Jul. 2011 – Sept. 2011	Undergraduate Intern	ICT, Chinese Academy of Science, China

#### **Publications**

- Xiaowei Ren, Daniel Lustig, Evgeny Bolotin, Aamer Jaleel, Oreste Villa, and David Nellans. "HMG: Extending Cache Coherence Protocols Across Modern Hierarchical Multi-GPU Systems", *26th International Symposium on High Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA)*, San Diego, USA, February 2020. (acceptance rate: 48/248 = 19.4%)
- Xiaowei Ren, and Mieszko Lis. "High-Performance GPU Transactional Memory via Eager Conflict Detection", 24th International Symposium on High Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA), Vienna, Austria, February 2018. (acceptance rate: 54/260 = 20.8%)
- Xiaowei Ren, and Mieszko Lis. "Efficient Sequential Consistency in GPUs via Relativistic Cache Coherence", 23rd International Symposium on High Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA), Austin, USA, February 2017. (acceptance rate: 50/224 = 22.3%)

- Pengju Ren, Xiaowei Ren, Sudhanshu Sane, Michel A. Kinsy and Nanning Zheng, "A Deadlock-Free and Connectivity-Guaranteed Methodology for Achieving Fault-tolerance in Direct Networks", *IEEE Transactions on Computers (TC)*, 2016. (acceptance rate: 30%)
- Xiaowei Ren, Qihang Yu, Badong Chen, Nanning Zheng, and Pengju Ren, "A Reconfigurable Parallel Accelerator for the Kernel Affine Projection Algorithm", *IEEE International Conference on Digital Signal Processing (DSP)*, Singapore, July 2015.
- Xiaowei Ren, Qihang Yu, Badong Chen, Nanning Zheng, and Pengju Ren, "A 128-way FPGA Platform
  for the Acceleration of KLMS Algorithm", Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASPDAC), Tokyo, Japan, January 2015. (University LSI Design Contest)
- Xiaowei Ren, Qihang Yu, Badong Chen, Nanning Zheng, and Pengju Ren, "A Real-time Permutation Entropy Computation for EEG Signals", *Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC)*, Tokyo, Japan, January 2015. (University LSI Design Contest)
- Xiaowei Ren, Pengju Ren, Badong Chen, Jose C. Principe, and Nanning Zheng, "A Reconfigurable Parallel Acceleration Platform for Evaluation of Permutation Entropy", 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), Chicago, USA, August 2014.
- Xiaowei Ren, Pengju Ren, Badong Chen, Tai Min, and Nanning Zheng, "Hardware implementation of KLMS Algorithm using FPGA", *International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*, Beijing, China, July 2014.
- Pengju Ren, Qingxin Meng, Xiaowei Ren, and Nanning Zheng, "Fault-tolerant Routing for On-chip Network without Using Virtual Channel", ACM/EDAC/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC), San Francisco, USA, June 2014. (acceptance rate: 3150/10963 = 29%)

#### **Awards**

2019 – 2020	UBC Graduate Student Initiative (GSI) Awards
2018 – 2019	UBC Graduate Student Initiative (GSI) Awards
2017 – 2018	UBC Graduate Student Initiative (GSI) Awards
2016 – 2017	UBC Graduate Student Initiative (GSI) Awards
2012 - 2015	National Master Scholarship (honors top 5% students)
2013 – 2014	Suzhou Industrial Park Scholarship
2010 – 2011	CASC Secondary Class Scholarship
2009 – 2010	National Motivational Scholarship (honors top 5% students)
2008 – 2009	Siyuan Scholarship

## Research Projects

- Architectural Support for Efficient GPU Synchronizations
  - Extending Cache Coherence Across Hierarchical Multi-GPUs NVIDIA Research
     Identified necessity of coherence hierarchy for performance scaling in multi-GPU systems. By leveraging the latest scoped GPU memory model, proposed, implemented, and evaluated HMG, a hierarchy

archical hardware cache coherence protocol for multi-GPUs. HMG not only avoids full cache invalidation in software coherence protocol, but also filters out write invalidation messages and transient coherence states. Despite minimal hardware overheads, HMG can achieve 97% of the performance of an idealized caching system. Published in the HPCA-2020.

- GPU Hardware Transactional Memory (TM) University of British Columbia
  Identified excessive conflict detection latency as a key limitation of performance and available parallelism in prior GPU TM proposals. Designed, implemented, and evaluated GETM, the first GPU hardware TM with eager conflict detection. GETM relies on a novel logical-timestamp-based conflict detection mechanism: conflicts are detected eagerly when the initial memory access is made. Performance is up to 2.1× better than the best prior work WarpTM (1.2× gmean). Area overheads are 3.6× lower and power overheads are 2.2× lower. Published in the HPCA-2018.
- Efficient Sequential Consistency (SC) in GPUs University of British Columbia
  Identified acquisition of write permissions as the main source of inefficiency in coherence protocol design for SC in GPUs. Developed, implemented, and evaluated RCC, an invalidate-free coherence protocol which grants write permissions without stalling but can still enforce SC. RCC is 30% faster than the best prior SC proposal for GPUs, and within 7% of the best non-SC design. Additionally, RCC allows for switching strong and weak consistency models at runtime with best-in-class performance and no hardware overhead. Published in the HPCA-2017.
- Light-weight GPU Cache Coherence Protocol NVIDIA Research
   Implemented, and evaluated a light-weight cache coherence protocol for NVIDIA GPUs to avoid the expensive cost of entire cache invalidation in software coherence protocol.
- Scalable Graphics Rendering in Multi-GPU Systems University of British Columbia Identified redundant computation and sequential inter-GPU synchronization as critical performance bottlenecks of existing SFR (Split Frame Rendering) implementations. To eliminate the overheads, designed, implemented, and evaluated CHOPIN, a sort-last rendering scheme by taking advantage of mathematical properties of image composition to compose pixels in parallel. Developed a draw command scheduler and an image composition scheduler to address the problems of load imbalance and network congestion. Compared to the best prior SFR implementation, CHOPIN can offer speedups of up to 1.56× (1.25× gmean). (Submission Under Review)

#### • Domain-Specific Accelerators

- Sparse Training Accelerator University of British Columbia
   In a group of three students, identified problems of designing a hardware accelerator for training sparse neural network directly, including load imbalance, dataflow etc. Proposed, designed, and evaluated a hardware-friendly sparse training algorithm, an accelerator architecture to enable sparse training, and a novel dataflow for load-balancing without complicating the on-chip network. (Submission Under Review)
- FPGA Accelerators for Computation-intensive Algorithms Xi'an Jiaotong University
   Designed, and implemented several FPGA accelerators for kernel-based machine learning and signal processing algorithms. Published in three conference papers and two student design contest papers.
- Fault-tolerant Network-on-Chip Routing Algorithm Xi'an Jiaotong University

  Proposed, implemented, and evaluated a deadlock-free, fault-tolerant routing algorithm for on-chip network that guarantees maximal connectivity without using virtual channels. With 40% link damage, the

algorithm guarantees 98% reliability with only 1% hardware overhead. Published in the Design Automation Conference (DAC) 2014 and the IEEE Transactions on Computers.

- Memory Model Checking Algorithm Max Planck Institute for Software Systems
   Proposed, and implemented efficient handling for spin-loops and barriers in stateless model checking.

### Talks & Presentations

- Oral, "HMG: Extending Cache Coherence Protocols Across Modern Hierarchical Multi-GPU Systems", HPCA, San Diego, USA, February 2020.
- Oral, "High-Performance GPU Transactional Memory via Eager Conflict Detection", *HPCA*, Vienna, Austria, February 2018.
- Oral, "Efficient Sequential Consistency in GPUs via Relativistic Cache Coherence", *HPCA*, Austin, USA, February 2017.
- Oral and Poster, "A 128-way FPGA Platform for the Acceleration of KLMS Algorithm", *ASP-DAC*, Tokyo, Japan, January 2015.
- Oral and Poster, "A Real-time Permutation Entropy Computation for EEG Signals", *ASP-DAC*, Tokyo, Japan, January 2015.
- Poster, "A Reconfigurable Parallel Acceleration Platform for Evaluation of Permutation Entropy", *EMBC*, Chicago, USA, August 2014.
- Poster, "Hardware implementation of KLMS Algorithm using FPGA", IJCNN, Beijing, China, July 2014.

## **Teaching Experience**

Jan. 2017 – Apr. 2017	Teaching Assistant, University of British Columbia, Canada	
	EECE527: Advanced Computer Architecture (Instructor: Mieszko Lis)	
Sept. 2016 – Dec. 2016	Teaching Assistant, University of British Columbia, Canada	
	CPEN <sub>4</sub> II: Computer Architecture (Instructor: Mieszko Lis)	
Sept. 2015 – Dec. 2015	Teaching Assistant, University of British Columbia, Canada	
	CPEN2II: Introduction to Microcomputers (Instructor: Tor Aamodt)	